Guide to the Victor Remer Historical Archives of the Children's Aid Society 1836-2006 (bulk 1853-1947) MS 111
New-York Historical Society
- Series XI - Records of the Children's Emigration, Placing-Out, and Foster Home Programs, 1853-2006; 1853-1939
  - Subseries X1.1 - Broadsides, Pamphlets, Reports, and other Materials, circa 1867- circa 1994
    - Information on former "orphan train riders" [compiled by an individual in the Orphan Train Heritage Society] (photocopies), circa 1970's (Offsite-box 45, Folder 35)
    - Compilation of facts about railroads used, station stops, towns of placement, and early statistics 1853-1920's, circa 1994 (Offsite-box 45, Folder 36)
  - Subseries X1.2 - Correspondence from Children and Foster Families, Chronological, 1855-1914; 1861-1881
    This subseries consists of 11 boxes of correspondence to the Children's Aid Society from children who were placed out in the country, and from the foster families who cared for them. The material is arranged chronologically, grouped by month, from 1855-1914 (bulk 1861-1881). Box 53A contains a volume of 1877 correspondence discovered and processed after the rest of the CAS collection was processed, creating a slight break in chronological order. That box also contains 1 tintype, which is the only photographic material in this subseries. There is only one folder of material 1884-1886 and one folder 1900-1914.
    The letters, originally glued or posted into scrapbook-style volumes, were in poor condition at the time of the donation of the collection. The scrapbook volumes, most of which were missing covers, have since been disbound, and the letters treated to remove glue and dirt. Index pages and pages with lists of children are included in the subseries, if such pages were extant.
    Each piece of correspondence was marked by the CAS recipient with a cross-reference to the volume and page number of the record book in which the child's records were kept. Those record books are arranged in Series XI.4.
    The correspondence in this subseries includes a few letters from former CAS wards writing as soldiers in the Civil War. There is a 13 year gap between the bulk of the final material in this subseries and the earliest material of the following subseries, XI.3, which also contains correspondence from children and foster families.
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1855-1859 (Offsite-box 46, Folder 1)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Lists of Children Placed by CAS 1855-1869, from correspondence volumes (Offsite-box 46, Folder 2)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Index pages to correspondence volumes, 1860-1869 (Offsite-box 46, Folder 3)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1860 (Offsite-box 46, Folder 4)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1861 January (Offsite-box 46, Folder 5)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1861 February (Offsite-box 46, Folder 6)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1861 March (Offsite-box 46, Folder 7)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1861 April (Offsite-box 46, Folder 8)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1861 May (Offsite-box 46, Folder 9)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1861 June (Offsite-box 46, Folder 10)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1861 July (Offsite-box 47, Folder 1)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1861 August (Offsite-box 46, Folder 2)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1861 September (Offsite-box 47, Folder 3)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1861 October (Offsite-box 47, Folder 4)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1861 November (Offsite-box 47, Folder 5)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1861 December (Offsite-box 47, Folder 6)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Lists of Children Placed, 1861 (Offsite-box 47, Folder 7)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, circa 1861 (Offsite-box 47, Folder 8)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1862 (Offsite-box 47, Folder 9)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1863 January-June (Offsite-box 47, Folder 10)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1863 July (Offsite-box 47, Folder 11)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1863 August (Offsite-box 47, Folder 12)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1863 September-October (Offsite-box 48, Folder 1)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1863 November-December (Offsite-box 48, Folder 2)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1864 January-February (Offsite-box 48, Folder 3)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1864 March (Offsite-box 48, Folder 4)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1864 April (Offsite-box 48, Folder 5)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1864 May-October (Offsite-box 48, Folder 6)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Lists of Children Placed, 1864 May-1866 July (Offsite-box 48, Folder 7)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, circa 1864 (Offsite-box 48, Folder 8)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1865 January-March (Offsite-box 48, Folder 9)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1865 April (Offsite-box 48, Folder 10)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1865 May (Offsite-box 49, Folder 1)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1865 May (Offsite-box 49, Folder 2)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1865 June (Offsite-box 49, Folder 3)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1865 June (Offsite-box 49, Folder 4)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1865 July-December (Offsite-box 49, Folder 5)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, circa 1865 (Offsite-box 49, Folder 6)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1866 February-June (Offsite-box 49, Folder 7)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1866 July (Offsite-box 49, Folder 8)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1866 August (Offsite-box 49, Folder 9)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1866 September (Offsite-box 49, Folder 10)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, circa 1866 (Offsite-box 49, Folder 11)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1867 February-March (Offsite-box 50, Folder 1)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1867 April (Offsite-box 50, Folder 2)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1867 May (Offsite-box 50, Folder 3)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1867 June-August (Offsite-box 50, Folder 4)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received and Company List, circa 1867 (Offsite-box 50, Folder 5)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1868 (Offsite-box 50, Folder 6)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Index for Correspondence and Lists of Children Placed, 1868-1869 (Offsite-box 50, Folder 7)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1869 January-February (Offsite-box 50, Folder 8)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1869 March (Offsite-box 50, Folder 9)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1869 April (Offsite-box 50, Folder 10)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1869 May (Offsite-box 50, Folder 11)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1869 June (Offsite-box 50, Folder 12)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1869 July (Offsite-box 50, Folder 13)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1869 August (Offsite-box 50, Folder 14)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1869 September (Offsite-box 51, Folder 1)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1869 October (Offsite-box 51, Folder 2)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, circa 1869 (Offsite-box 51, Folder 3)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, undated circa 1860-1869 (Offsite-box 51, Folder 4)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1872 January-March (Offsite-box 51, Folder 5)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1872 April (Offsite-box 51, Folder 6)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1872 May (Offsite-box 51, Folder 7)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1872 June (Offsite-box 51, Folder 8)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1872 July-August (Offsite-box 51, Folder 9)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1872 September (Offsite-box 51, Folder 10)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1872 October-November (Offsite-box 52, Folder 1)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1872 December (Offsite-box 52, Folder 2)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1873 January-February (Offsite-box 52, Folder 3)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1873 March (Offsite-box 52, Folder 4)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1873 April (Offsite-box 52, Folder 5)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1873 May (Offsite-box 52, Folder 6)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1873 June (Offsite-box 52, Folder 7)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1873 July (Offsite-box 52, Folder 8)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1873 August (Offsite-box 52, Folder 9)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1873 September (Offsite-box 52, Folder 10)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1873 October (Offsite-box 52, Folder 11)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1873 November-December (Offsite-box 52, Folder 12)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1873 (Offsite-box 52, Folder 13)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1875 (Offsite-box 52, Folder 14)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Index to Correspondence Received, 1876-1877 (Offsite-box 53, Folder 1)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1876 January-March (Offsite-box 53, Folder 2)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1876 April-June (Offsite-box 53, Folder 3)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1876 July (Offsite-box 53, Folder 4)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1876 August (Offsite-box 53, Folder 5)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1876 September (Offsite-box 53, Folder 6)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1876 October (Offsite-box 53, Folder 7)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1876 November (Offsite-box 53, Folder 8)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1876 December (Offsite-box 53, Folder 9)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1877 January (Offsite-box 53, Folder 10)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1877 February (Offsite-box 53, Folder 11)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1877 March (Offsite-box 53, Folder 12)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1877 April-December (Offsite-box 53, Folder 13)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, undated, circa 1876-1877 (Offsite-box 53, Folder 14)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1878 January-February (Offsite-box 53, Folder 15)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1878 March (Offsite-box 53, Folder 16)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1876 November-1877 January (Offsite-box 53A, Folder 1)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received and one tintype, 1877 February (Offsite-box 53A, Folder 2)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1877 March (Offsite-box 53A, Folder 3)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1877 April (Offsite-box 53A, Folder 4)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1877 May (Offsite-box 53A, Folder 5)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1877 June (Offsite-box 53A, Folder 6)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1877 July (Offsite-box 53A, Folder 7)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1877 August (Offsite-box 53A, Folder 8)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1877 September (Offsite-box 53A, Folder 9)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1877 October (Offsite-box 53A, Folder 10)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Index for 1877 correspondence volume and undated correspondence (Offsite-box 53A, Folder 11)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, original binding for 1877 correspondence volume (Offsite-box 53A, Folder 12)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1878 April (Offsite-box 54, Folder 1)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1878 May (Offsite-box 54, Folder 2)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1878 June (Offsite-box 54, Folder 3)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1878 July (Offsite-box 54, Folder 4)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1878 August (Offsite-box 54, Folder 5)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1878 September (Offsite-box 54, Folder 6)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1878 October (Offsite-box 54, Folder 7)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1878 November (Offsite-box 54, Folder 8)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1878 December (Offsite-box 54, Folder 9)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1879 January (Offsite-box 54, Folder 10)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1879 February (Offsite-box 54, Folder 11)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1879 March (Offsite-box 54, Folder 12)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1879 April (Offsite-box 54, Folder 13)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1879 May (Offsite-box 55, Folder 1)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1879 June (Offsite-box 55, Folder 2)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1879 July (Offsite-box 55, Folder 3)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1879 August (Offsite-box 55, Folder 4)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1879 September-December (Offsite-box 55, Folder 5)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, circa 1878-1879 (Offsite-box 55, Folder 6)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, undated, circa 1870-1879 (Offsite-box 55, Folder 7)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1880 January-February (Offsite-box 55, Folder 8)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1880 March-April (Offsite-box 55, Folder 9)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1880 May-June (Offsite-box 55, Folder 10)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1880 July (Offsite-box 55, Folder 11)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1880 August (Offsite-box 55, Folder 12)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1880 September (Offsite-box 55, Folder 13)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1880 October-December (Offsite-box 55, Folder 14)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1881 January (Offsite-box 55, Folder 15)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1881 February (Offsite-box 55, Folder 16)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1881 March-August (Offsite-box 55, Folder 17)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, circa 1880-1881 (Offsite-box 55, Folder 18)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Correspondence Received, 1884-1886 (Offsite-box 55, Folder 19)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Miscellaneous Undated Correspondence Received, circa 1860-1886 (Offsite-box 55, Folder 20)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Miscellaneous Correspondence Received, 1900-1914 (Offsite-box 55, Folder 21)
  - Subseries X1.3 - Case Files, 1895-1951; 1895-1939
    This subseries consists of 913 boxes of case files of children placed in homes or work situations by the Emigration/Placing-Out and Foster Home Programs of the Children's Aid Society. Most case files include application forms from prospective foster families or employers, reports of visits or updates on the children by CAS agents, correspondence to the Children's Aid Society from children who were placed out in the country, and/or from the foster families or employers who cared for them. There are also many photographs.
    The material is housed in boxes 56-964, and the files are arranged by case file number. The numbers were assigned roughly chronologically around the time the child came under the care of the CAS. These case files cover children placed between 1895-1951 (bulk 1895-1939). There is material in the case files from later dates, if correspondence or other contact occurred in subsequent decades. Boxes 56-688, containing case files numbered 1-10,347, from 1895-1916, are cross-referenced to the volumes in subseries XI.4. Boxes 965-968 contain miscellaneous case files 1895-1930, numbered 15,000-15,353 and unnumbered. All numbers above 15,000 were assigned by Victor Remer in the 1980's. Boxes 968-969 contain case files grouped alphabetically from the 1920's-1940's.
    This finding aid does not list the individual folders in boxes 56-969, because the case files are RESTRICTED and the names in the records are sealed. The N-YHS reference department maintains a list of all photographs, tintypes, and selected visual materials in the case files. Please contact the reference department for further information about access to case file materials. Researchers whose primary interest is tracing family history will be put in contact with a designated Children's Aid Society specialist who will interview the potential researcher to determine what he or she may consult and will then supervise the reader's use of the appropriate material. Guidelines currently in place for family history research at CAS, as determined by legal restrictions on the accessibility of adoption and foster care records, will be followed. See Access Restrictions, at the top of this finding aid.
    - Emigration/Placing-Out and Foster Home Programs, Case Files 1-14,141, 1895-1951 (Box 56-964)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out and Foster Home Programs, Case Files 15,000-15,353 and unnumbered, circa 1895-1930 (Box 965-968)
    - Emigration/Placing-Out and Foster Home Programs, Case Files - Alphabetical, circa 1920's-1940's (Box 968-969)
  - Subseries X1.4 - Emigration/Placing-Out Program, Bound Volumes, 1853-1930; 1853-1916
    This subseries consists of 100 bound volumes related to children placed in homes or work situations by the Emigration/Placing-Out Program of the Children's Aid Society, 1853-1930 (bulk 1853-1916). The volumes are arranged in 2 sub-subseries, which overlap and complement each other:
    Sub-subseries XI.4.A consists of Surrender Volumes which document children turned over by their guardians to the custody of the Children's Aid Society, Company Volumes which list children by the groups in which they traveled to the country together, and various other volumes listing placements, applications for children, financial records, and other records of the Emigration Program 1853-1922. The volumes are arranged chronologically by the initial date of the volume. Some of the volumes in XI.4.A are RESTRICTED, as per the Deed of Gift by which the collection was donated to the N-YHS. Restricted volumes are labelled as such in this finding aid and on the volumes themselves.
    Sub-subseries XI.4.B consists of a set of record books numbered 1-57 by the CAS, describing children's cases in rough chronological order 1855-1916, preceded by an index to those record books 1853-1906. The information in these record books complements the correspondence and case files in Series XI.2 and XI.3, which cross-reference these volumes. All of the material in XI.4.B is RESTRICTED.
    Researchers who wish to view restricted children's files or restricted volumes should contact the library of the New-York Historical Society. These researchers will be referred to a designated Children's Aid Society specialist who will interview the potential researcher to determine what he or she may consult and will then supervise the reader's use of the appropriate material. Guidelines currently in place for family history research at CAS, as determined by legal restrictions on the accessibility of adoption and foster care records, will be followed.
    Families who traveled out west as part of the Family Emigration Program are listed in the Company Books and Record Books, but for volumes dedicated specifically to the Family Emigration Program 1874-1926, see Series XII.2.
    - Sub-Subseries XI.4.A - Emigration/Placing-Out Department Volumes, 1855-1922
      Subseries XI.4.A consists of 42 volumes produced by the Emigration/Placing-Out program of the CAS between 1853-1922. The volumes overlap with the volumes in the following subseries, XI.4.B. The materials include Surrender Volumes which document children turned over by their guardians to the custody of the Children's Aid Society, Company Volumes which list children by the groups in which they traveled to the country together, and various other volumes listing placements, applications for children, financial records, and other records of the Emigration Program 1853-1922. The volumes are arranged chronologically by the initial date of the volume. Some of the volumes in this sub-subseries are RESTRICTED. Restricted volumes are labelled as such in this finding aid and on the volumes themselves.
      - Reference Book 1 (Narrative of children taken in and dispositions), 1853-1854 (Offsite-box 1057, Volume 362)
      - Reference Book 2 (Narrative of children taken in and dispositions into 1860's), 1854-1855 (Offsite-box 1058, Volume 363)
      - Company Book 1, 1854-1863 (Volume 364)
      - Some Children Placed Out, arranged alphabetically by town and state, 1854-1869 (Offsite-box 1058, Volume 365)
      - Surrender Book, arranged alphabetically by child, 1854-1869 (Volume 366)
      - Applications for Children, in narrative style, 1855 (Offsite-box 1058, Volume 367)
      - Surrender Book (1 folio), 1862 (Volume 368)
      - Emigration Statistics, 1862-1870 (Offsite-box 1058, Volume 369)
      - Surrender Book, 1863-1872 (Volume 370)
      - Company Book 2, 1863-1875 (Volume 371)